Finding Aid for Wilma T. Donahue Papers 1945-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Videotapes: White House Conferences as Agents of Social Change, 1979
  - Hauser, Philip M., "Social Morphological Revolution in Population: Explosion, Implosion, Displosion, and Techniplosion,", May 30, 1979 (Box 21)
    (Tapes 1-3)
  - Boulding, Kenneth E., "Uncertainty and Probability for the Future,", May 30, 1979 (Box 21)
    (Tape 4)
  - Neugarten, Bernice N., "Old Old and Young Old,", May 30, 1979 (Box 21)
    (Tape 5)
  - Butler, Robert O., "Our Future Selves,", May 30, 1979 (Box 21)
    (Tapes 6 and 7)
  - Health Maintenance System and Care (Panel Discussion), May 30, 1979 (Box 21)
    (Tapes 8-9)
  - Education in the Future Society (Panel Discussion), May 30, 1979 (Box 21)
    (Tapes 10-11)
  - Mission of White House Conferences on Aging (Panel), May 31, 1979 (Box 22)
    (Tapes 1-2)
  - Older Persons Contribution to the Nation (Panel), May 31, 1979 (Box 22)
    (Tape 3)
  - Financial Security and the Changing Economy, May 31, 1979 (Box 22)
    (Tapes 5-6)
  - Evolving Roles and Careers of Older People, May 31, 1979 (Box 22)
    (Tapes 9-10)
  - Social Impacts of White House Conferences on Aging, June 1, 1979 (Box 22)
  - Old Age in Other Countries, June 1, 1979 (Box 22)
    (Tapes 3-4)
- International Center for Social Gerontology
  International Center for Social Gerontology [boxes 23-25] documents Donahue's professional activities 1973-1982 when she was director of this Washington, D.C. agency. The files are arranged alphabetically by topic and primarily contain material on efforts to improve housing for the elderly during the 1970s. The many grant applications in this series are good sources of information, because they provide explanations of the intent and scope of the many programs designed by the ICSG.
  The first program undertaken by the ICSG was the 1973 "International Symposium on Housing and Environmental Design for Older Adults." One outcome of the symposium was a study of congregate housing in the United States and Western Europe. Congregate housing provides housing for older adults who require some personal assistance and housekeeping services but do not require the medical care provided by a nursing home. A second outcome was the formation of the International Clearinghouse Study Committee on Housing and Environmental Planning for Older Adults (1974-1975). The International Clearinghouse studied methods for improving the dissemination of information resources in the areas of aging, housing, environmental planning, as well as how these resources were used.
  From 1973 to 1977 the ICSG was involved in developing and promoting a Vacation Residential Exchange Program for Older Adults. The program offered travel opportunities for older adults who lived in public housing. From 1975 to 1978 the ICSG developed sheltered housing in Maryland. Sheltered housing is congregate housing for older semi-independent adults. The Maryland program was later expanded into a national program, the Housing Technical Assistance Program (H-TAP). H-TAP developed educational materials on and offered training in housing the aged for state and local agencies. The program ran from 1977 to 1982.
  The last significant project undertaken by the ICSG under Donahue's leadership was a 1979 symposium titled "White House Conferences as Agents for Social Change." The symposium provided input for the congressionally-mandated 1981 White House Conference on Aging.
  - Aging around the world, 1980 (Box 23)
  - Aging: Broadening the Xerox Leadership, 1979 (Box 23)
  - Center for Community Change (Box 23)
  - Congregate Housing
    - Bibliography, U.S. and Western Europe, 1977 (Box 23)
    - Conference Planning Committee, 1975 (Box 23)
    - Conference Proposal, 1975 (Box 23)
    - Definitions and Taxonomy (Box 23)
    - Final Report for the U.S., 1978 (Box 23)
    - Grant Request, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Indian Hills Project, Cleveland, OH, 1977 (Box 23)
    - Interim Reports
      - European, 1975 (Box 23)
      - U.S., 1975 (Box 23)
    - New Jersey Conference, 1977 (Box 23)
    - Paris Conference
      - General, 1975 (Box 23)
      - Planning, 1975 (Box 23)
    - Progress Report, U.S., 1974 (Box 23)
    - Resource Book (Washington, D.C. Conference), 1975; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - State Questionnaire Results, 1975; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Study Report, 1975 (Box 23)
  - Elderly Ex-mental patients in Hospital and Community Care, grant request, 1981 (Box 23)
  - Housing the Deinstitutionalized Elderly Mentally Ill Conference, 1981 (Box 23)
  - Housing Technical Assistance Program (H-TAP)
    - Advisory Committee, 1978 (Box 23)
    - Final Reports, 1982 (Box 23)
    - Grant Request
      - 1977 (Box 23)
      - 1978 (Box 23)
      - 1979 (Box 23)
    - Institute, Virginia, 1980 (Box 23)
    - Memos, 1978 (Box 23)
    - Minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 23)
    - Publications (Box 24)
    - Readings on Housing and Services for Older Adults, 1980 (Box 24)
    - Rural Congregate Housing, 1981 (Box 24)
    - Survey, 1977
      - Region 1 (Box 24)
      - Region 2 (Box 24)
      - Region 3 (Box 24)
      - Region 4 (Box 24)
      - Region 5 (Box 24)
      - Region 6 (Box 24)
      - Region 7 (Box 24)
      - Region 8 (Box 24)
      - Region 9 (Box 24)
      - Region 10 (Box 24)
      - Summary of Responses (Box 24)
  - International Clearinghouse Study Committee on Housing and Environmental Planning
    - General, 1975; 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Grant Applications, 1974-1975 (Box 24)
    - International Documentation Study on Housing and Related Facilities and Services for Older Adults, Findings and Conclusions, 1975 (Box 24)
    - International Information Analysis and Resource Center on Aging (Box 24)
    - Questionnaire on Information and Data Use, 1975 (Box 24)
  - International Symposium on Housing and Environmental Design for Older Adults
    - Fund raising, 1973 (Box 24)
    - Proposal, 1973 (Box 24)
    - Recommendations, 1974 (Box 24)
    - Student Competition, 1973 (Box 24)
  - Maryland
    - Conference on Sheltered Housing
      - Proceedings
        - 1975 (Box 24)
        - 1978 (Box 24)
      - Program and Speakers, 1978 (Box 24)
    - Guide for Sponsors of Sheltered Housing, 1976 (Box 24)
    - Sheltered Housing Description (Box 24)
    - Survey, 1977 (Box 24)
    - Training Project Progress Reports, 1977 (Box 24)
    - Training and Technical Assistance Program in Sheltered Housing for the Elderly
      - General
        - 1975-1976 (Box 24)
        - 1977 (Box 24)
        - 1978 (Box 24)
      - Contract and Proposal, 1975 (Box 24)
      - Preliminary Evaluation, 1977 (Box 24)
      - Tenant Selection, 1977 (Box 24)
  - Pennsylvania Contract, 1974-1975 (Box 25)
  - Pennsylvania Report, 1975 (Box 25)
  - Task Force on the Establishment of a Clearinghouse on Housing and Living Environments for Older Adults, 1973 (Box 25)
  - Testimony of Donahue before the House Select Committee on Aging, 1981 (Box 25)
  - Testimony of Donahue, "Manpower Problems in Social Services for the Elderly", 1976 (Box 25)
  - U.S. and Foreign Information Sources on Housing the Elderly, 1977 (Box 25)
  - Vacation Residential Exchange Program (VRE)
    - Feasibility Study Final Report, 1974 (Box 25)
    - Final Report
      - 1974 (Box 25)
      - 1978 (Box 25)
    - Grant Request
      - 1973 (Box 25)
      - 1974 (Box 25)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 25)
    - Planning, 1973-1974 (Box 25)
    - Planning Manual, 1977 (Box 25)
    - Planning Manual for Local Housing Authority Sponsors, 1977 (Box 25)
    - Profile of Exchanges, 1974-1975 (Box 25)
  - White House Conferences as Agents for Social Change, Symposium
    - Final Report, 1982 (Box 25)
    - Findings, 1979; 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Grant Proposal
      - 1978-1979 (Box 25)
      - (information dissemination), 1980 (Box 25)
    - Lectures, 1979 (Box 25)
    - Materials, 1979 (Box 25)
    - Program and Participant Materials, 1979 (Box 25)
- Miscellaneous
  The final series Miscellaneous [box 27] contains a variety of materials that came to the Bentley Historical Library after Donahue's death. This series overlaps in many ways the previously described materials, but also fills in gaps by providing some personal correspondence and a little information about Donahue's teaching activities in the 1960s and her research interests in the 1980s. This accession has been divided into six short subseries.
  - Alumnus Place
    Alumnus Place documents a failed proposal made by Donahue and her colleagues at the University of Michigan to build an education-oriented retirement community for University of Michigan alumni and faculty. Envisioned as a continuing education center for retirees, the plans for Alumnus Place never came to fruition.
    - Communications, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Proposal, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Planning, 1984-1985 (Box 26)
  - Biography
    Biography includes curriculum vitae and brief biographies of Donahue written for various purposes during her life. Also here are the transcripts of an oral history of the Institute of Gerontology in which Donahue, Clark Tibbits and Woodrow Hunter are interviewed. The third subseries, Correspondence, has been placed in chronological arrangement by year, with the exception that there is a separate folder for 1989 correspondence about the writing and publication of Memoirs in Aging, a history of gerontology in Michigan.
    - Curriculum Vita, Bibliographies and Biographies, undated (Box 26)
    - History of Institute of Gerontology, 1978-1983; 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Michigan Women's Studies Award, 1983 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence
    - Chronological, 1969-1970; 1982-1990; 10 folders (Box 26)
    - Memoirs on Aging, 1989 (Box 26)
  - Geriatric Education
    Geriatric Education includes materials written by Donahue on the topic of educating gerontologists. It includes five subseries: Inter-University Training Project in Social Gerontology, Summer Institute in Social Gerontology, Seminar in Aging, Training in Gerontology, and IOG History. These files document the development of geriatric education at the University of Michigan as well as Donahue's role in it.
    - Inter-University Training Project in Social Gerontology
      - Minutes and Agendas, 1957-1959 (Box 26)
      - Press Releases, Budgets, Progress Reports, 1958-1959 (Box 26)
    - Summer Institute on Social Gerontology, 1956-1960 (Box 26)
    - Seminar on Aging, 1968 (Box 26)
    - Training in Gerontology, 1967 (Box 26)
  - Speeches and Writings
    Speeches and Writings is organized chronologically where dates are known, and topically for undated items. This subseries spans 1950-1987. The sixth subseries, Photographs, contains two photographs of Wilma Donahue taken in the later part of her career.
    - Chronological, 1950-1987; 5 folders (Box 26)
    - Topical
      - General, undated (Box 27)
      - Mental Health, undated (Box 27)
      - Geriatric Education, undated (Box 27)
      - Housing, undated (Box 27)
  - Travel Writings, 1954-1966 (Box 27)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits and miscellaneous (Box 27)